<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the Christian Sabboth a godlye treatise of Mayster Iulius of Milayne / translated out of Italian into English, by Thomas Langley.</title>
            <author>Julius, of Milan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1552</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24522525</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24522525</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the Christian Sabboth a godlye treatise of Mayster Iulius of Milayne / translated out of Italian into English, by Thomas Langley.</title>
                  <author>Julius, of Milan.</author>
                  <author>Langley, Thomas, d. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[63] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules churcheyarde, at the signe   of the George by Willyam Reddell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>mense Maio [May] 1552.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabboth a godlye treatiſe of mayſter Iulius of Milayne, tranſlated out of Italian into Engliſh, by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Exod. xx.</bibl>
               <p>¶Remembre that thou kepe holye the Sabboth daye.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1552. <hi>Menſe Maio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:2"/>
            <head>¶ To hys verye entier frende mayſter William Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of London, Thomas Laug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley wiſheth grace and peace in Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE diſcipline of good conuerſation (gentle Mayſter Lewes) ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth chieflye, or rather altogether in ij. poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: that is, in doctrine, and exerciſe. By doctrine is taught to know what ſhould be done, by that other, men be broughte to cuſtome, that they be willinge &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to put in execution that, which they haue learned. And the one of theſe with out the other is maymed &amp; vnperfecte. Wherfore Moyſes ſemeth to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken better fourme of gouernement, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any politike ruler of the heathen, in his lawes makynge. For where the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians and Cretians ordered al by doinges and vſe, withoute muche a do makyng in wordes: and contrary wiſe the Athenians ſpente longe ſpace in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees making, but were ſlacke in requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the performaunce of the ſame: Moyſes moſt diligently hath coupled
<pb facs="tcp:27758:3"/>
And ioygned them ſo together, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he parted good cuſtome of liuynge from doctrine, nor ſuffered doctrine to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out inuring of workes. But becauſe they ſhoulde agreablye be matched, he aſwell made lawes for reſte and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of workes, as he did for the dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of labour to be occupied, not that theyre ceaſynge from workes ſhoulde mayntayne idlenes and ſlouth, but that therby they might be guyded by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and that their offences ſhoulde not be cloked or excuſed by ignoraunce. For that daye, that they reſted (whyche they named therfore the Sabboth, and was not ones or twyſe in the yeare, but euerye weke ones on the ſeuenth daye) they came together to here the lawe of God, wherin was conteyned all ſuche thynges, as they ſhoulde do and expres in their behauiour.</p>
            <p>The maner of their comming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as Philo telleth) was thus. When the ordinarye day came, they aſſembled to their temples with muche ſpede, and there did ſitte geuing good audience, &amp; diligenteare to the ſcriptures, onleſſe at tymes wyth one accorde, they ſpake a word in commendation of that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:27758:3"/>
there ſaide, &amp; redde, and the prieſt or one of the elders reherſed the lawe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it, and this faſhion they vſed at the ſeuenth day, till the euening tide, and then departed. By meanes wherof they neded not to aſke of the lawiers what they ſhoulde do, nor coulde be in their euill diſcharged by any colored ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of lacke of knowledge, but the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to the wife, the father to his chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, maiſters to their ſeruauntes, decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the commaundementes of the law. Thus was doctrine taught one daye, &amp; exerciſe and practiſe all the weke after, was put in execution, and vſed.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer labour letted them from reſorting to the hearing of the law, was ſtraightly forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſharpe payne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for correction of the offendours therin. Nowe if this preciſe order was vſed on the Sabboth daye, vnder Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; his doctrine ſo duely taught, and all to bringe men to a ciuill order, &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward righteweſnes: howe muche more nedefull is it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we, which profes chriſt, be buſied in learninge the lawes of the goſpel, the law of the ſprite, the word of life, which whoſoeuer knoweth, ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue for their obedience &amp; honeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation
<pb facs="tcp:27758:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:6"/>
not only reward temporal in this life, but alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſoules, &amp; life euerlaſtinge. Let it not therfore greue vs, which be in the daylight of the goſpell, on the dayes of aſſembling together deuoutly to vſe our ſelues: ſeing the Hebrues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were hud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the cloudy ſhadow &amp; letter of the lawe, ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo willing &amp; forwarde to obſerue the ſame. For albeit the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſh Sabboth touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth day be abrogated &amp; expelled, yet is not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth ſanctifiyng diſanulled, but remaineth ſtil as a head<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful part of chriſtian religion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyning all ſuch due ſeruice, as belongeth to the glory of god. And for that cauſe our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (when otherwiſe blind ignoraunce had ouerſhadowed the hole world, that the Sabboth might reuerently be halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) ordeyned by act of parlament, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thys realme no fayres nor markettes ſhuld be kept vpon the ſonday, or other ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne feaſt, as vpon chriſtmas day, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter day, with ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day, &amp; aſcenſion day, as appeareth in the actes of Henry the .vi. king of this realme. But nowe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our knowledge we ſhould be better: tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough vnbrideled libertie, we be growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:6"/>
to ſuch badnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al (law of god &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſet aſide, men be wholy geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer to folow their luſtes on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth daies, not only by going to markets, fayres, &amp; gaſinge games, but alſo by miſuſing their time, (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld be ſpent in reading or hearing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, in praier, and viſiting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore) in beare baiting, hauking, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting, da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſing, carding, diſing, ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quetting &amp; other kindes of riot &amp; ſurfetting. And thus make thoſe daies moſt vnholy of al the weke, &amp; worthier to be named idle dayes for their euil occupiyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, then holy dayes for any halowed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: where our reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> workes of body ſhould be an earneſt exerciſing of oure ſprites in gooſtly doinges. Wherfore it is to be wiſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a reformation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe might be taken therin by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, for the reſtoring of the ſabboth to it owne propre kinde. And becauſe I perceaued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this treatiſe of maiſter Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius of Milayne, declareth &amp; handleth this matter at large, I thought good (ſo as I coulde) to turne it into oure natiue ſpeche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reders might learn what their office is on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, &amp; ſe how far we be ſwarued oute of frame from the true natural vſe therof.
<pb facs="tcp:27758:7"/>
And albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> argument be vniuerſall, &amp; mete for all men for the matter, yet it ſpecially ſemeth verye fitting, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicated to your ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes: aſwel for that you be geuen to the ſtudy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Italian tong (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by reading herof you mighte be an Ariſtarchus to examine how nere I haue gone to the Italian Phraſe, &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author) as alſo becauſe it was my duty to ſhewe ſome teſtimony vnto you, of the good hert y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I haue borne to you, euer ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re firſt conuerſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t together, in familiaritie of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, and conference of ſtudy, whiche as it began long agone, ſo hath it ſtil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued, fixed &amp; ſtedfaſt on my behalf. Pleaſeth it you therfore to accept in good part this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmall in quantitie, but great both for godlines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke, &amp; good will of the preſenter, &amp; chiefly for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is your wont ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes to ſet muche by any gift, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your herty frendes. And I ſhal dailie, as occaſion &amp; oportunitie ſerueth further vtter my faithfull loue toward you, by ſuche thynges as my habilitie ſhalbe ſufficient to perfourme, &amp; be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuall petitioner to god for youre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſe healthe longe to endure. Fare you hertelye well. From Headcrone the .xxi. of Marche. 1552.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:7"/>
            <head>¶Of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, that hath ben more myſtaken of the Scrybes and Phariſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodely obſeruaunce and kepynge of the Sabboth daye. Becauſe that God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned it not, to the intente that the outwarde ryght and vſage of forbearynge worke and bodelye laboure, ſhoulde with ſo muche religion, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcrupuloſite be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but the Sabboth was inſtituted, to be as it were a ſhadowe and figure of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall reſte, from fleſhly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, which a Chriſtian ought
<pb facs="tcp:27758:8"/>
continually to practiſe, &amp; put in vre in hys liuyng and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. In conſideration wherof, we read that our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt had lytle reſpect and leſſe reuerence to that It wiſhe ceremonye of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, and buſelye laboured to perſwade the Iewes, that to put difference betwixt dayes was rancke ſuperſtition, and ſtarcke hypocriſye. Wherfore he dyd manye workes on the ſelfe Sabboth day:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth. x. ij</note> he healed the man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had the wythered hande,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc. vi.</note> on the Sabboth daye. The Apoſtles rubbed out the eares of corne to eate, on the Sabboth daye:<note place="margin">Iohn. v.</note> he healed at the pond by the ſlauter houſe the man that had bene xxxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yeares diſeaſed,<note place="margin">Iohn. ix.</note> he cauſed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the blynde borne to ſe: and
<pb facs="tcp:27758:8"/>
ſayeth thys daye in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell:<note place="margin">Iohn. vij.</note> if a man breake not the Sabboth in circumciſynge a chyld, why are ye greued and wode wyth me, becauſe I haue healed a man on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daye?<note place="margin">Luc. xiiij.</note> We reade in S. Luke that oure mayſter hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the Sabboth a man di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeaſed wyth the dropſey, and the Phariſeis, as theyr wont maner was, murmured, and grudged at that deade. But oure mayſter opened, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed euidentelye forthe that, their erroure with thys aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſaying. Which is there amonge you, if hys oxe or aſſe ſhoulde fall into a pitte on the Sabboth daye, that woulde not do his beſte to rydde hym oute, &amp; yet were not the Sab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>both broken therby. And the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:9"/>
reaſon therof our mayſter ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth, where he ſayeth, The ſonne of man is Lorde of the Sabboth: that is, man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Sabboth, and in his affayers ſhould not haue any eye or conſideration to the corporall ceremonye, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of it. But becauſe the Iewiſh Sabboth hath bred, and brought forth great hypocriſye in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian churche, it is expedient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and neadfull, that we wayg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and examine, in what maner man was Lorde of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, afore that Ieſu Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffered, to thintente that the libertye of dayes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue in the Chriſtian congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, now ſyth that Chriſt hath ſuffered and is aſcended into heauen, maye be the better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:9"/>
more throughly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And leſt peraduenture any errour or falſe opinion ſhoulde grow in the beginning of this talke, thou muſte vnderſtande that all ſawes, that be founde anye where, eyther be naturall or poſityue.</p>
            <p>Naturall lawes be thoſe,<note place="margin">Natural lawes.</note> that the Lord God hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the naturall reaſon of man, whyche afterwarde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge written in the ſtonye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by mynyſterye of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were made playner, and more open, then they were be fore in our conſcience. As for example, the lawe of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of God, of reuerenſing his name, of obeyinge our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, and other ſuperiours, of not robbynge, of not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittynge adultery, of not kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:10"/>
and finally of not doyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to others that we would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were done to oure ſelues. Theſe be called by the nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Goddes lawes, not onely becauſe God appoynted the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Moyſes, but alſo for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord hath prynted them in the mynde of euerye liuing man. Whych thynge Sayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paule declareth, where h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſayeth,<note place="margin">Rom. ij.</note> that the heathen ſhew the workes of the lawe writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in theyr heartes, they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne conſcience bering the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> witnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.<note place="margin">Two ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitiue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</note> Lawes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue (which haue theyr orig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall of the lawes of nature b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of .ij. ſortes. For ether they be Eccleſiaſticall or elles the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be cyuill Eccleſiaſticall lawes whych in the olde Teſtamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are called ceremoniall)<note place="margin">Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall lawes.</note> wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:10"/>
ordeyned for the conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of true fayth, and pure reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the churche of God.<note place="margin">Of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</note> Of theſe lawes there were a greate numbre amonge the Hebrues, as the circumciſion, the Sabboth, the order of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,<note place="margin">Lawes of the new. Act. ij.</note> and all the leuiticall obſeruaunces. Lykewyſe in our Chriſten churche there is the inſtitution of baptiſme, of the Lordes ſupper,<note place="margin">1. Cor. xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge the Goſpell, of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and collection, or collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the pouertye, wyth all ſuche other lawes, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the mynyſterye of the word, and of the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Theſe lawes be of God, inſomuche as they be appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by God in the newe and olde Teſtamentes. <hi>Semblablye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach lawes as be added to theſe, to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that the churche maye be gouerned
<pb facs="tcp:27758:11"/>
in formall order wythoute confuſſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. xiiij Col. ij.</note> 
               <hi>oughte to be called Goddes lawes,</hi> Wherfore Paul, hauynge ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an order in the publike hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye, comlynes, and modeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> behauioure, that ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued in the congregation, aſwell in men, as in women, ſayeth theſe wordes: if anye man thynke hym ſelfe a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher or ſpiritual,<note place="margin">1. Cor. xiiij</note> let him know what thynges I wryte vnto you, for they are the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord God? Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the church or aſſemblye of the faithfull, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye thynge muſte be handled in order with diſcretion, with confuſed minglynge.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde ſort of lawes poſytyue be ciuyll,<note place="margin">Ciuill lawes.</note> or politike and Iudityall lawes, whyche are deuyſed for the kepynge
<pb facs="tcp:27758:11"/>
of the publike peace, common quiet, and vneuerſall honeſtye in all ſtates of men. Theſe were long ago made and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by God to Moyſes, and ſyth Moyſes tyme euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hathe inuented theyr pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and ſeueral lawes, and conſtitutions. Whych in lyke maner be named the lawes of God, not onelye becauſe that Moyſes enacted them, <hi>but alſo becauſe that princes, common weales &amp; other officers be the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of god,</hi> to punyſhe malefactours, and promote y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good doers.<note place="margin">Rom. xiij</note> Paul ſayeth: there is no power but of God, and the powers that be, are ordeyned of god. Now that theſe thynges be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, let vs ſe, which of the fore ſayd lawes, a man in the time of Moyſes, and before that
<pb facs="tcp:27758:12"/>
Chriſt had died, was Lord of and aboue: that is, whiche of them he might in caſe of nead breake, and omitte. Fyrſt and formeſt I ſaye to you: that the lawes natural,<note place="margin">Lawe of nature ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be broken for anye cauſe</note> be of ſuch force &amp; ſtrengthe, that nether they ought nor maye be broken for any kinde of neceſſitye or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hofe, whatſoeuer: but a man is bound to neglect honour, ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches, deſpyſe hymſelfe, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne hys owne lyfe, rather then tranſgreſſe the lawe of nature. For ſoner a man ſhuld entre the fire, then denie god, and be more willing to abyde hangynge by the necke, then blaſpheme the name of God, he oughte redilyer dye anye kynd of terrible and dredeful death, then beare falſe witnes agaynſt his neyghboure. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:27758:12"/>
there is no maner thing that more ſtraightly bindeth vs, nor more narowly kepeth vs in, and (as it were) pinneth vs vp, then dothe the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to god: nether can there be anye greater ſcourge ouer our heade, then that is due for diſobeying the Lorde. For it behoueth that all our neades, all our perillous daungers, al our profitable commodities, geue place and rowme to the obedience of god: for that we alwayes obeye to God, it is neadfull, but to continue ſtyll in thys lyfe mortall, ſtandeth not in ſuch neceſſitye. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawes, that is,<note place="margin">Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall lawes be diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed with.</note> eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ciuyll, albeit they be ordeyned of god, yet be not ſo holye and reuerente, but that they may in cauſes of neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:13"/>
not only be broken, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo altogether dyſanulled, as though they neuer had bene. And for profe herof, let vs per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uſe the eccleſiaſticall lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. Thoſe lawes were to be kepte, and done, ſo longe as the outward gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of the Iewes endured, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that Chriſt was dead and ryſen agayne: they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of God by the handes of Moyſes, for the people of Iſraell, to the ende, that the name of God ſhould be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the promiſes made in Chriſt myghte be taught, and true religion preſerued, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was circumciſion, the ſab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bothe, the ſacrifices, &amp; all that ſolemne and ceremoniall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and leuiticall obſequies aboute the tabernacle of the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:13"/>
Iewes, ordeyned and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for any other purpoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is afore ſayde. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, for ſo muche as theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes were onlye geuen to the people of the Iewes, &amp; to none other nation, therfore the gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiles, and foreyne people were not burdened, nor charged, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kepinge of thoſe ſtatutes, nether did they offend in not kepynge them, for that they were not driuen to liue vnder thoſe conſtitutions, although they had forſaken Idolatry, and acknowledged one very God, by beleuyng the promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Ieſu Chriſt. We reade,<note place="margin">Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple.</note> that the people of Niniue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented at the preachynge of Ionas, &amp; pleaſed,<note place="margin">Iones. iij.</note> and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God therby,<note place="margin">Niniue.</note> yet reade we not, that they were circumcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:14"/>
nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they obſerued other eccleſiaſtical lawes of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.<note place="margin">Daniel. iij</note> Daniel wytneſſeth,<note place="margin">Babilon</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the king of Babilon confeſſed ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the very true god of Iſrael, &amp; commaunded by proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that no man ſhould blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme him, neuertheleſſe it is not reade, that the king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilon was therfore bownden to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ceremonies of Moyſes. No the Iewes them ſelues were not ſo bounden to theſe eccleſiaſticall lawes, but that they myghte omitte them in tyme of neade, ether for anye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, or for anye matter of honeſtye. Many of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites after theyr deliuerye out of Egypt, while they were in the wildernes, were vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed as it appeareth in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue.<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue. v.</note> And very likely it is that
<pb facs="tcp:27758:14"/>
manye Iewes died in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte wythoute circumciſion,<note place="margin">foreſkin.</note> whiche by faith paſſinge from death vnto life, were not da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for hauynge theyr fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkin. King Dauid fleinge the perſecution of Kynge Saul,<note place="margin">i. Re. xvij.</note> leſt he ſhould dye for hunger,<note place="margin">Shewe bread.</note> did eat (both he and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany) of the table of the lord, the holy bread, that was dedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated, &amp; appoynted onely for the vſe of the prieſtes, and yet ſinned he not in ſo doing. By thys example of Dauid oure maiſter proueth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, that in neadfull affayres and buſynes,<note place="margin">Math. xij.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of man (that is, euery man) is Lorde of the ſabboth. Nether did oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte by theſe wordes, meane that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both ſhould not, or oughte not
<pb facs="tcp:27758:15"/>
to be kept at that time, when as yet he was not deade, be ſhewed therby, on what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ceremonies of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bounde that nation to the obſeruynge of them. For the Iewiſhe ceremonies (at that tyme) were to be reuerenced by the generall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of God,<note place="margin">Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</note> notwythſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if ether nede, or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of any neighbour conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned a Iew to breake them, he was not in ſuche caſe bownde to kepe them, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (cauſe ſtanding) the Iewes was lord of the Sabboth, and offended not in breakynge and omyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge them.</p>
            <p>Therfore our ſauiour Chriſt ſynned not, when he healed ſicke and diſeaſed perſons on the ſabboth day, becauſe that
<pb facs="tcp:27758:15"/>
neceſſity, &amp; neyghbourly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye cauſed him to haue ſmall reſpect to the outward Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, which was a ſhadowe &amp; figur of the chriſtian ſabboth. So ſone as chriſt was deade and riſen agayne, all the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Iewes were vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly diſanulled and repelled: wherfore the Chriſtian man was vnburdened of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of them, &amp; only truſted to be ſaued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God ſhewed in Ieſu Chriſte. For this cauſe we chriſtians ought not to make any difference of dayes, nor thynke that one daye is holyer then another. Wherfore S. Paul wold not that a chriſtian,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> iudge &amp; think any diuerſity betwene day &amp; day,<note place="margin">Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor that any man ſhoulde accuſe vs for any faſtiual day,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:16"/>
or new mone, or ſabboth day, and feared leſt he had trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in vayne, in the churche of the Galathians,<note place="margin">Gal. iiij.</note> becauſe they were obſeruers of dayes: wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng to do vs to vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to count one day holier then that other, was a thing, that parteyneth to a Iewe, &amp; not to Chriſten men.</p>
            <p>That, whych we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ceremonies Moſaicall,<note place="margin">Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note> namely that in neade, &amp; other behoues they bound not anye Iewe, we may lykewiſe ſaye and affirme of the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lawes of Chriſtendome wherof ſome be autoriſed by Ieſu Chriſt, and ſome by the father &amp; elders of our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chriſten fayth myght be preached and taughte in good order. And albeit the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinances
<pb facs="tcp:27758:16"/>
of our aunceſtours, be not to be compared to thoſe that god the lord appointeth, yet are they to be obſerued, &amp; ought to be reuerently vſed, becauſe that god wold, that in the churche, thynges ſhuld be ordered in comly maner, and wyth due reuerence. But for ſo much as theſe our lawes ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remoniall are made for oure commodity, &amp; not to our loſſe, therfore the lord would that they ſhould yeld, &amp; geue place to oure neceſſityes.<note place="margin">Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is a di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> There be many chriſten men vnder the Turke in vylanowſe ſlauery, which can not vſe the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Lordes ſupper, &amp; yet ſhall they not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therefore, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue the fayth of Ieſu Chriſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other be entangled &amp; chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb facs="tcp:27758:17"/>
in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnares of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes hypocriſy, whych can not here the ſincere preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell, &amp; yet ſhal not for that cauſe be condemned, if in the meane while they do beleue &amp; truſt in Ieſu Chriſt, al ſuch do not ſin, becauſe neceſſity excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lyke proceſſe might be made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuditial lawes, but I wyll not at thys tyme make any treatiſe vpon them.</p>
            <p>The Phariſeis therfore, mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued of an hatefull hypocriſye, blamed our maiſter, as a wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked breaker of the ſabboth, &amp; yet vnderſtode not for what purpoſe God had ordeyned the Sabboth. The Lord had an higher reſpecte, then to the bodely reſt, when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſabboth in the law, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to the Iewes: Remembre
<pb facs="tcp:27758:17"/>
that thou kepe holy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth daye,<note place="margin">Exo. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſyxe dayes ſhalte thou worke, and the ſeuenth is the Sabboth of the lord thy god, thou ſhalt do no worke there on.<note place="margin">Iuſtituti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the ſabboth.</note> In thys ſpeche God prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallye ſheweth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſraell, that a man can not be ſanctified nor iuſtified by hys owne workes, but proueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to come to holines, behoueth to kepe gooſtly ſabboth. This is purport and intent of thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, namely that we oughte to be deade to the workes of our owne fleſh, for beare and reſt from ſinne, and continually haue our medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; ſtudy of the kyngdome of god: practiſinge our ſelues in this gooſtly reſt, we ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the chriſten Sabboth. For thys conſyderation it is (I
<pb facs="tcp:27758:18"/>
thynke) that Auſten (writyng vnto Ianuarius) ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 12.</note> that this commaundemente of the ſabboth is figuratiue, &amp; a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow touching the outwarde keping of the daye, whiche is cleane abrogated together, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all other ſhadowes and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Moſes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Ieſu Chriſt. Wherfore aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient writers ſaye,<note place="margin">thre cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth.</note> that God appointed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment of the ſabboth for thre cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fyrſte cauſe.</note>Fyrſt, becauſe the lord vnder the commaundemente of the bodely reſt, wold haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded the ſpirituall &amp; gooſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly quiet, wherin the faythfull ſurceaſſe from fleſhly workes, &amp; geue place to god, to worke in them the workes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gooſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Seconde cauſe.</note>The ſeconde cauſe why the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:18"/>
Sabboth was commaunded to the Iewes, is that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Hebrues myghte haue an appointed to heare the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The thyrde cauſe is, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes,<note place="margin">Thirde cauſe.</note> and ſuch as be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection and vnder the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement or rule of others, may haue ſome eaſe and diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce of labour.</p>
            <p>Thus, albeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we find how the ſabboth was inſtituted for thre cauſes aforeſaide, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, the principall and chiefe cauſe why this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niall commaundemente was geuen, is becauſe it ſhuld ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify &amp; importe to vs, the reſte from ſinne, &amp; halowing of our ſoules and mindes. For thys cauſe we read in the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, that there was no com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement
<pb facs="tcp:27758:19"/>
ſo preciſely and ſtraightly geuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes,<note place="margin">Exo. xxxv.</note> as the keping of the Sabboth was, when god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al religion was deſtroied and waſted among the Iewes,<note place="margin">Hier. xvii</note> he lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth that this ſabboth is broken,<note place="margin">Qezech. xx</note> that it is not kept not ſanctified, as though the lord ſhuld ſay:<note place="margin">ſabboth is all reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the ſabboth is defiled &amp; deſpiſed, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no other thing wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyth God can be honoured. Wherfore the lord commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the religion of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, aboue all other ſpiritual workes, ſpeaking to hys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on this wiſe: take heade (o ye childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye kepe my ſabboth,<note place="margin">Exo. xixi.</note> becauſe it is a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne betwene me and you, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough out your generation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may knowe, that I am the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:19"/>
lorde that ſanctifie you. Kepe the ſabboth, for it is holy vnto you, it is an euerlaſtyng coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt betwene me &amp; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſraell, and a perpetual ſigne. By theſe wordes of the Lord is well perceaued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſabboth is a ſigne, wherby the people of Iſrael may know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is their ſanctifier. A chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man can not become holy, onleſſe firſt of al he crucify the euil deſires of his carnal wyl. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraight keping of the ceremonial ſabboth is not the thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can make vs holy, but it is a ſhadow, and ſygne, which teacheth vs to leaue of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fleſhlye workes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſprite of the lord maye worke in vs the true ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">gooſtlye ſabboth.</note> ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the carnal wil of the chriſten man, ſhould geue place to the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:20"/>
ſprite of god, his worldly hert to the wil of god. Our bodye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the carnal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhuld reſte from voices &amp; al diſhoneſt workes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god may do in vs hys holy and gooſtly workes. This is that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſabboth, &amp; chriſten holy day, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule deſcribeth to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues,<note place="margin">Heb. iij.</note> where he ſayeth: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there remaineth a reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the people of god.<note place="margin">Heb. iiij.</note> For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is entred into his reſt, ceaſſeth from his workes,<note place="margin">Gene. ij.</note> as god dyd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys, let vs make haſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to entre into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſte. And forſomuch as a true chriſtian oughte alwayes to ſubdue &amp; kepe vnder the fleſh with it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupiſcences &amp; luſtes,<note place="margin">Continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</note> he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery howre kepeth ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, &amp; taketh not one daye to be more holy then another.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:20"/>This our ſpirituall ſabboth we begin in this mortal lyfe, &amp; from daye to day (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of the ſprite of god encreaſeth in vs) we more and more reſte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of the fleſhe, &amp; be more feruent &amp; forward in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge the ſabboth.<note place="margin">fleſh bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both. Gal. v.</note> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh continually wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth &amp; ſtriueth agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprite and abateth him from the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecte loue therfore no chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (whileſt he abideth in this fleſh) kepeth throughly &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the ſabboth, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding at the laſt, when we ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be coupled to Ieſu Chriſte, &amp; the kingdome ſhalbe reſigned into the handes of god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">1. Cor. xv</note> &amp; god ſhalbe al in al, then ſhall we kepe the perfect ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both. This is that perpetual ſabboth, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall holy day,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:21"/>
that Eſay the Prophet deſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beth ſaying:<note place="margin">Eſay. lxvi</note> there ſhalbe ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both after ſabboth, and newe mone after new mone, whych alſo was reſembled &amp; ſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of the lord god to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, in the outwarde ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the ſeuenth day. This is that ſabboth, for whych the Prophet ſo much bewayleth, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked went about to take it quite away from the earthe,<note place="margin">Pſa. lxxiij</note> ſayinge: come of, let vs take euery ſabboth of god out of the earthe. Other ſabboth then thys do not the chyldren of God acknowledge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is, to ſtaye &amp; truſt in the merites of Ieſu Chriſt,<note place="margin">Chriſten ſabboth.</note> by meane wherof they be iuſtified, and crucifye their owne fleſhe. And forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as a chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redly certified &amp; knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
<pb facs="tcp:27758:21"/>
hath god for hys father, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he layeth al his trauayl &amp; grefe vpon him, which taketh care for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful kepe Sabboth, when they ſay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes prayer, o lorde thy wyll be done. By theſe wordes the faythfull is reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp; fulfilled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprit of the lorde, &amp; knoweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not behouefull to folowe hys carnal wil, that the wil of god might be done, &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhed. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the brother of Chriſt, is guyded by the comfortable ſprite, &amp; not by the wyſdom of of his fleſh. Whether death, or life, ſhame or honoure, riches, or pouerty, trouble, or proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity come, the chriſtian man is nether diſmayed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſpayre, nor puffed vp in pride. For he kepeth diligently the ſabboth
<pb facs="tcp:27758:22"/>
of the ſprite, &amp; taketh it for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is in the handes of god. Happy be thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that ſanctify the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Sabboth in their hertes, yea more then happy maye I call them, for they are no more in diſpayre of conſcience, they know how much Ieſu Chriſt worketh in theyre myndes, they paſſe not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhadowes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be diſanulled &amp; deſtroyed by the coming of the body of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt. O vnhappy be oure dayes wherin raygneth more ſuperſtition, then euer dyd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Iewes. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meruelous chere, &amp; reioyſing that the Prophet maketh for the ſolemnitie of the day, dedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated to the lord, ſaying: ſing wyth triumphe vnto god our helper,<note place="margin">Pſa. lxxx.</note> make ye melody to the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:22"/>
god of Iacob. Lifte vp youre ſwete tunes of the cymbales: ſmite vpon your Pſalters, &amp; touche clenly the ſtrynges of your ſwet harpes, blow your trompettes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of your new mone, &amp; in the ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne day of your feaſt. This ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; tune of the Prophet was expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Paule, wher he ſayeth:<note place="margin">Col. iij. Epheſ. vj</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld in our hertes ſinge to the lord Pſalmes, &amp; ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſonges, reioyſing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprit, and ioyinge in thys ſabboth. Wherfore faith ioygned with true confeſſion, &amp; loue, maketh vs to ſing to the verye god of Iacob. This reioyſing is kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen outwardly of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, by the confeſſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we make in the name of the great God.<note place="margin">pſaltery</note> The Pſalterye that we ſmyte on in the ſolemnitye of
<pb facs="tcp:27758:23"/>
this ſabboth is the louynge &amp; thanking of god.<note place="margin">Cimbal.</note> The cimbal is the mortifyinge of humane wyſdome, the crucifying of all mannes merites, &amp; the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of al ſuperſtitiouſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Harpe.</note> The harpe, that is played vpon in the feaſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth, is the charitie, that we vſe to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward our neighbour, whyche cauſeth oure conuerſation to be dulcet, and pleaſaunt. The trompet is the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel,<note place="margin">Tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet.</note> wherwith all chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be ſomoned &amp; warned to ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the feaſt of the ſabboth, for in Ieſu Chriſte is ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtynge Sabboth.</p>
            <p>This is the tyme that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the lord,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. vi. Eſay. xli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in which he hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth vs, for this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, wherin he ſuccoureth vs. Therfore the chriſtian ſab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>both
<pb facs="tcp:27758:23"/>
is, that a man diſpayre of him ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he condemne his owne holynes, &amp; all that, that can come of our owne nature, and put the truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of his ſaluation in one only Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt. By this meane man reſteth from hys carnall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and geueth place for the lord to worke in hys hert the doinges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprite, wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde conſecrateth vs, &amp; halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs into hys owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, as the Prophete ſayeth: The lorde that made euerye thing gouerneth al,<note place="margin">Pſal. xci.</note> for al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges be in hys handes.<note place="margin">Iewes offended</note> The Iew &amp; the hipocrit, that here talke of thys maner ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſabboth daye, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, yea and is ſtarcke woode, his bloude chafeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hym, nether can he abyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:24"/>
the ſuperſtitiouſe ceremonie of daies be ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. On other ſide the faythfull man heareth thoſe thynges,<note place="margin">the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.</note> reio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, is glad, &amp; chereful in hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hert ſayinge: Prayſed be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lord, in whoſe handes &amp; cuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is my ſaluation:<note place="margin">Ihon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I am w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſured to be ſaued, for no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can take or pull me out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> handes of the eternall fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Sabboth therfore is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> halowed by being ydle,<note place="margin">Idlenes is not ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowyng</note> nor ſtanding with the fingers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the girdle, nor yet wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ceaſing from hand labour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> day, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſtitiouſe Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſuppoſeth. Wherfore we re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Prophet Eſay, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſanctifiyng of the ſabboth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth not in the outward &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely religion of the holy d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but the true halowing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing
<pb facs="tcp:27758:24"/>
our owne wil, &amp; glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g the lorde. For he ſayeth, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou tourne thy fete from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abboth,<note place="margin">Eſay. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> lviji.</note> ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou do not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing which pleaſeth thy ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my holy day, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> called vnto the pleaſaunt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly &amp; glorious ſabboth of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd, where thou ſhalt be in ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do not after thyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne ymagynatyon, nether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke thine owne wil, nor ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hyne owne wordes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou haue thy pleaſure in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord, whych ſhal cary the high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boue the earth, &amp; fede thee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he heritage of Iacob thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her. Nether is there anye doubt, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ceremony of the day is abrogated by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Ieſu Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye of time ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated.</note> like as al other ceremonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es be. Ieſu Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth,
<pb facs="tcp:27758:25"/>
at whoſe preſence all figure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be deſtroyed. Ieſu Chriſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye, at whoſe approchin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al ſhadowes vaniſhe awaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he alone hath geuen vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true fulfylling of the ſabboth by clothyng vs with hymſelf throughe his death,<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being raiſed agayne with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might leade a newe life, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore all our lyfe ſhuld be a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petual ſabboth, as I haue ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to you before.</p>
            <p>And although there be no d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferences of dayes in the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian congregation,<note place="margin">Rom. xiiij</note> yet wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Paule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the weake in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were borne with, &amp; ſuffered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that compaſſion be take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon ſuche, as be fre from a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kynde of hypocryſye and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſimulation, becauſe manye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue alredy ſome knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:27758:25"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the word of God, deſyre to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſtyll forwarde. But for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey be felle as chyldren, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ryſhed and noſeled in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſtes religion, they beleue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat one daye is more holye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en another, of more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce, and more honour then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother, of this hypocriſye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rked vp in the ſwathlynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>des, ſpringeth vp alſo this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther erroure, that the conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of the hypocrite &amp; ſimple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cloyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcrupuloſity: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinketh that he committeth as it is commonly termed) a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>adly ſynne, if on the holye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay he ſhould go to plowing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do any other maner of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oure. The Apoſtle ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re wolde,<note place="margin">Weake muſt be borne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</note> that ſuche feble &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eake in the fayth ſhuld not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>raight way be deuided from
<pb facs="tcp:27758:26"/>
the churche. For with allo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; charitable maner, our du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is fyrſt to enſtructe them, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do them to perceyue &amp; witte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of what ſorte the chriſtien <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> euangelical liberty is, which is purchaſed &amp; bought for v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by Ieſu Chriſt. Afterwarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when the weake faythed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taught ſo farre, that he kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth the libertye of dayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of meates, of rayment, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all other outwarde workes and neuertheleſſe wyll be fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde, and refuſe to enioye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> chriſten liberty, then in ſuche caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infirmitie is no leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be borne with, or ſuffered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bycauſe ſo it myght growe to be vncurable. This errour was bytterly blamed of S. Paule, which inflamed with great grefe, rebuked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church
<pb facs="tcp:27758:26"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Galathians, ſayinge:<note place="margin">Gal. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> if ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue alredy knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye tourne backe a freſhe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weake and beggerlye ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntes, wherto ye would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>unden &amp; thrak ſeruauntes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ayne? Ye obſerue dayes, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>onethes, and tymes, &amp; yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, I am in feare of you, leſt I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue beſtowed labour on you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vayne.<note place="margin">Two cauſes neuer ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogated</note> The other two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, for whyche the ſabboth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Iewes was inſtytuted, were neuer abrogated in any age or tyme: but ought to be obſerued of Chriſten men in the newe teſtamente, with no leſſe earneſtnes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were of the Iewes in the old lawe. Wherfore it is expedient and mete, that amonge vs be dayes appoynted, when the church ought to aſſemble and
<pb facs="tcp:27758:27"/>
come together to heare the preaching of the word of god,<note place="margin">Act. ij.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Holye day beha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour.</note> to vſe ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lordes ſupper, to make common prayer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of chriſtendome, to make collections of almes for the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lefe of the poore,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vi</note> &amp; that famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es &amp; houſholdes may be infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the chriſten religion, &amp; godlines, to viſite our fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in a chriſtien maner, to viſite the ſycke, &amp; to practyſe ſuche other lyke holye dedes. Youth of it ſelfe is vnruly &amp; headye. The vplandiſhe &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faythed, ſone falle into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,<note place="margin">Holye dayes be deadfull</note> wherfore it is neceſſary for this intent to ordeyne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dayes, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youthe may be nurtred, and kept in awe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that the ignoraunte may learne to knowe, what chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion is, and what ſeruice
<pb facs="tcp:27758:27"/>
is due to be geuen to god.</p>
            <p>The thyrde cauſe, wherfore the ſabboth was dyuiſed, is open &amp; playne by the wordes, that the lord ſpake to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue people. Thou ſhalte ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue &amp; take hede (ſayeth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſeruaunte, and thy mayde reſt them, remembre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou was a ſeruaunte in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and of Egypt. For theſe two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſes therfore, that be cyuill, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e chriſtians muſt haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n and determinated dayes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the church may continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> exerciſed &amp; inured, aſwel in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardly in workes of the ſprit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outwardly in loue toward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur neighbour. For this conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ration the law of the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bad the Iewes, only ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orkes on the ſabboth daye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> letted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they could
<pb facs="tcp:27758:28"/>
haue no leaſure or reſpyte to heare the worde of God,<note place="margin">Why worke is forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> to do the ordinary oblations and ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifices, to make publike pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, and other exerciſes, full of charitye, and loue. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, they were forboden to tyll the land, to buyld houſes, and to do any other ordinary labour on the ſabboth day, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch workes held a man buſied al the day, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend to no other thynge, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of the ſabboth was ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the Iewes, they ſynned not, if for neceſſitie, or for the weale &amp; profite of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour, they chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced ſome time to breake it, as I haue ſayde aboue in thys treatyſe.</p>
            <p>We Chriſtians be fre from thoſe ceremonies, and thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:27758:28"/>
ordynaunces,<note place="margin">Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be fre.</note> that the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes were in bondage vnder. Therefore no lawe of meate, of dayes, of clothynge, of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, can bynde vs to a ſynne, as it dyd the Iewes. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, for ſo muche as the church can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregated,<note place="margin">Dayes to what vſe.</note> and gathered, except there be dayes appointed, wherin the worde of God muſte be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, the lordes ſupper miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, publike prayer made, &amp; other Chriſten workes afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentioned muſt be practiſed: Therefore oure aunciente fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; elders, haue determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and inſtituted, that at the leſt one day of the weke ſhuld be beſtowed &amp; geuen to theſe religyouſe and deuout ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xvi.</note> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles church the Chryſtyans folowynge
<pb facs="tcp:27758:29"/>
the cuſtome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes came together on the ſabboth daye, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many yeares the holy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſtendom vſed the ſabboth, for the day dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the ſpirituall gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement. But afterward, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtendome increaſed, and ſpred abrode, in the tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great Conſtantine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes ſhuld haue no occaſion to glory againſt vs, &amp; that other ſhuld not think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Chriſtian man became a Iew, &amp; laſtly to declare to the whole world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one day is not more holy then another, the ſabboth was alte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red into the daye folowynge, which was named of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians the dominical day,<note place="margin">So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. i.</note> that is, dedicated to the lord. And the kepynge of thys day hath bene alwayes vſed, ſythen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:29"/>
in the church, thinges may be done with order, &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Now to proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es were ordeyned of our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours for thys polytycall ende,<note place="margin">Howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers vſed the ſabboth</note> &amp; not to make one daye holyer then that other,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4.</note> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the auctority of Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane In his boke againſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion: &amp; Hierome vpon the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Galathians, wher he ſayeth: leſt the vnordinary congregatynge of the people ſhuld miniſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith in Chriſt, therfore certaine dayes be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we myghte all mete together, not that, that day, wherin we mete, is more holy or reuerent, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more reioyſing may come of the mutuall beholding, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer day we mete. Saynte Auguſtine alſo in hys worke
<pb facs="tcp:27758:30"/>
               <hi>de ciuilate dei,</hi> maketh mention of certayne memorialles of holy dayes, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natiuity of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſion, the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrection, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſcenſion, &amp; whit ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day, on whiche daies y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians dyd acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, to vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, to make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers, &amp; do other chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian dedes. The ſame is red in the eccleſiaſtical hiſtorye of Euſebius. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oure elders, knewe that ceremoniall holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſabboth dayes, as the Iewes did. They onelye on thoſe dayes aſſemble for the ſame purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did,<note place="margin">Act. ii. The apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles vſe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daye.</note> whiche continued in doctrine, in prayer, breakyng of bread, &amp; in the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, in aydinge and rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the poore. And it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:27758:30"/>
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule appoynted the day of the ſabboth, on whiche day,<note place="margin">1. Cor. xvi.</note> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation came together, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the churche of Corinth ſhuld make theire collections of almes, that the poore chriſtians at Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which died for hunger, might be releued &amp; ſuccoured. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therfore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians be fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſuperſtitiouſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy of keping the ſabboth, &amp; other feſtiual dayes. The Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes among other feaſtes,<note place="margin">Iohn. x. Feſt of tentes.</note> did vſe to ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mſe a feaſt of taber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacles, ſo named becauſe they dwelled vij, dayes in pauilio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; bothes. This feaſt was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in remembraunce, that theire fathers dwelled in the deſert and wyldernes in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, when they were delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondage of Egypt.
<pb facs="tcp:27758:31"/>
According as the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded ſayinge: In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth moneth (whiche agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wyth the moneth of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober amonge vs) the .xv.<note place="margin">Leui. xxx.</note> daye of the moneth ſhalbe the holy day of the tabernacles, &amp; ſeuen dayes ſhall ye lodge in tentes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your poſteritye may knowe, how that I made the chyldren of Iſrael to dwell in bothes when I deliuered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of Egypt. Thys ſolemnitie ſhuld be kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hipocriſye, &amp; ſuperſtition, becauſe it was but only a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moryall, &amp; remembraunce of the benefyte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God had done to their fathers. But the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes forgetting the meanyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt, thought they ſhulde offende deadly, if on ſuch day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that were feſtyuall, they
<pb facs="tcp:27758:31"/>
had done anye bodelye &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke. In like maner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſeis expounded vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people the precept of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>both amiſſe. The lord ſayeth: thou ſhalte not worke on the ſabboth day. This commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement onlye bounde the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doynge ſuch labours, as letted the people, that they coulde not come to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſembly, to be exercyſed &amp; occupied in the law and wyl of the Lord, as I haue alredy ſayde here to fore.</p>
            <p>The laſte cauſe of kepynge the ſabboth was,<note place="margin">Reſte of ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes &amp; labouring perſons might haue ſome quyetnes &amp; releafe of laboure: neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Phariſeis neglecting the true vnderſtandinge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth, had bewrapped and
<pb facs="tcp:27758:32"/>
folden the people in the ſnare of hypocriſye and vayne ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. Ouer and beſydes this,<note place="margin">Phariſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>icall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</note> they added of their own heade infinite other obſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and rites, wherwith they brought the people into bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bondage, for they ſayd: on the ſabboth day men oughte not walke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graſſe, leſte it wyther, and be deade, nor clymbe trees, nor eate frute gathered on the ſabboth day, nor ryde on that daye, leaſte the Sabboth were broken, nor waſhe clothes that were filed, nor blende wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, nor kil a flie, nor fede anye thing, nor rede by ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>del light, onleſſe there be two at the leaſt together in a companye, and innumerable other ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtityouſe toyes they put to of
<pb facs="tcp:27758:32"/>
their owne brayne, by meane wherof they made the people ſuperſtitiouſe &amp; hypocrytes.</p>
            <p>And they were ſo earneſtly geuen to ſuch nouelties, that they forgate the weyghtye thynges of the lawe, that is, true faythe in God, mercye &amp; pytye towarde their neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Of ſuch thynges if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce they ſpake any thing to the people, it was done ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry coldely, becauſe they were ſtrayghte kepers of thynges of no value, and were ſatiſfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in magnifyinge theyr car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Sabboth,<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons blinded.</note> by whych mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes they ſo kepte vnder the vnderſtandynge of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, that they neuer came to the knowledge of the very truthe. But we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to whome is opened and
<pb facs="tcp:27758:33"/>
declared the goſpel, muſt kept a perpetual ſabboth in ſpryte. For to a chriſtian only belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the true reſt of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Canahan.<note place="margin">Heb. iiij.</note> If Ioſue had geuen the chyldren of Iſraell the true quyetnes, when he wente ouer Iordane, GOD wold not efteſones promyſe a true reſte, nor ſpeake of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſabboth by the Prophet Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſa. xxiiij</note> whyche was a longe while after Moyſes &amp; Ioſue. Therfore Ioſue was but a ſhadowe and figure of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. xiij. Ioſue a figure.</note> whyche geueth vs the verye reſt, &amp; ſpirituall ſabboth. Let vs kepe a ſpirituall &amp; gooſtlye ſabboth, and not a carnall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue not here anye continuyng citye, but we ſeke for one to come. Wherfore let vs (as Paul ſayeth) knowe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:33"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oure earthye houſe of thys dwellyng were deſtroyed,<note place="margin">ij. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we haue a buyldynge ordeined of god, an houſe not made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but euerlaſting in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, let vs lighted, eſtringe to be clothed with oure manſion, that is in heauen. And a lytle after he ſayeth, we that are in thys ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bernacle ſigh and are greued, for we had rather not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clothed, but be clothed vpon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortalytye myght be ſwalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vp of lyfe. Therfore, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſt we be in thys worlde, we can not perfectelye kepe the gooſtly ſabboth: for the fleſhe in ſuche ſorte combereth our thoughtes, that we can not ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> workes of the fleſhe, that the ſpryte of the Lorde myghte onlye in vs kepe the
<pb facs="tcp:27758:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27758:36"/>
gooſtly and heauenlye Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, and that we myghte be coupled wyth Ieſu Chriſte our heade, whyche hathe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs the true reſte, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynge into the moſt deſyred land of Canahan, by the path &amp; paſſage, that is made and ſette open by hys bloude. To whome be glorye worlde wythout ende.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>☞ Fautes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>The vij. leafe b. the laſte lyue for conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration reade conſeruation.</p>
            <p>The viij. leafe b. the xviij. lyue for with reade wythout.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:27758:36"/>
            <p>¶ Impryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at London in Paules churcheyarde, at the ſigne of the George by Willyam Reddell. In the yeare of oure Lord. 1552.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
